金星和水星
Mercury and Venus,
两个对立的世界有着完全不同的经历
two hostile worlds that suffered very different fates.
其中一个非常活跃 释放强大的自然之力
One, very much alive and seething with treacherous forces of nature.
另一个一片死寂
The other, a planetary carcass
形成于大量碰撞
gouged by millions of high velocity impacts.
都显示出恶劣环境下的行星上的恐怖
Both demonstrate the true horrors of planets gone wrong.
水星和金星近日行星
Mercury and Venus, the inner planets.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第7集 近日行星·水星和金星
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
沿着地球和火星
Along with Earth and Mars,
水星和金星组成了近日太阳系
Mercury and Venus make up our inner Solar System.
木星 土星 天王星 海王星
Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune,
一个比一个远离太阳
these planets farthest from the Sun
都是拥有着气态外表的远日行星
make up the gassiest outer worlds of the Solar System.
在40亿年里这些近日行星
Over 4 billion years, the inner planets
在太阳系内各种杂乱物质的碰撞与结合下形成了各自的固体结构
bound enough interstellar debris to become rock solid.
为什么我们研究行星
Why do we study planets? Why do we study…
为什么研究天文学
astronomy at all?
某天我们也许不得不离开地球
We some day need to go beyond the planet Earth
如果我们想永远生存下去
if we expect to survive as a species for a very long time.
我们必须了外面有些什么宇宙的性质是如何的
And we need to know what's out there and what the nature of the Universe is.
我们研究世界上任何感兴趣的事物
We're studying worlds where things are exotic,
不过基本的物理化学原理
but the basic processes of physics and chemistry at work
跟地球上的完全一致
are really the same we see here on Earth.
水星金星两石质兄弟 远在数百万英里外
Millions of miles separate us from our rocky cousins,
不过研究过水星和金星后得到了许多基本数据
but a tour around Venus and Mercury reveals a common DNA.
我们能够观测他们
We can go to Mercury and Venus and really look at these
研究他们的各项数据
as places, as worlds with their own histories,
并立即联想到地球的这些数据
and then contextualize our own planet's history.
体型上金星是太阳系中第6大行星
Venus is the sixth largest planet in the Solar System.
离地球最近时
At its closest,
大约距离2600万英里[4200万千米]
it is 26 million miles away from Earth.
一金星年等于225地球天
A year on Venus lasts 225 Earth days.
地球上150磅的物体
And if you weigh 150 lbs on Earth,
在金星上只有136磅重
you'd weigh 136 on Venus.
古罗马人观察金星
Venus, when the ancient Romans looked up,
他们被金星美丽的外表征服
they were captivated by its commanding presence.
称之为维纳斯--爱与美的女神
They named the planet after their serene goddess of love and beauty.
在空中显得如此美丽
It's such a beautiful presence in the sky,
很容易被观测到
it seems obvious the connexion there.
金星长期以来被当作地球的姐妹星
Venus has long been considered our sister planet
是因为相近的距离和相似的
because of its closeness in composition,
引力 密度与大小
gravity, density and size.
金星和地球在许多方面就像双胞胎
Venus and Earth are almost twins in a lot of ways.
几乎差不多大小 金星只是略小于地球
They're almost the same size. Venus is slightly smaller than Earth.
如果地球像篮球这么大 金星就像足球
So if Earth was a regulation basket ball, Venus is a soccer ball,
只小一点点 金星是地球最近的同伴
slightly smaller. And Venus is the closest planet to Earth.
以至于有人一直以为地球金星是一个双子星系统
So for a long time it was thought of literally as a twin planet.
长期以来科学家们认为这个伴星像地球一样
For ages, scientists thought this twin,
拥有深海
like Earth, was a planet covered with deep oceans,
大片雨林
lush rainforests,
还有悬崖以至于深信不疑
and had a climate that would give credibility
认为金星上也有智慧生命
to the notion that intelligent life could exist there.
太空时代以前人们普遍认为金星类似地球
Before the space age, people thought it might be very Earth-like on Venus.
当我们开始观测 探索金星 发现这些结果完全是谬论
But the paradox is, when we actually got to Venus and started exploring it,
发现那里环境跟地球大不相同
the conditions there are so different.
结果证明金星与其说是地球好姐妹
It turned out Venus was less of an exotic sister to Earth
不如说是个恶魔兄弟
and more of an evil twin.
两个行星基本数据十分相近
So here we have two very similar planets in their sort of bulk properties,
却最终进化成两个完全不同的形态
but they've evolved to such different states.
引出了一个关于行星演化的有趣问题
And that creates an interesting problem in understanding planetary evolution.
一些特定的反应
A sort of controlled experiment,
发生在两个行星上
take these two similar planets and let them go for…
不断演化数十亿年为什么造成了最后的巨大差异？
4 billion years, and then why do they end up so different?
首先一些基本的差别
First, some of the basic differences.
金星被陨星撞击
Venus has been hit hard with meteors.
其中一些撞击非常强
One so strong that
一些科学家认为这甚至导致了金星的反转
some scientists think it may have reversed the planet's rotation.
金星自转很慢
Venus has a very slow rotation.
我们称其为逆向自转
And it has what we call "retrograde rotation".
因为自转的方向不同于太阳系中所有其他行星
So it spins backwards compared to the direction of spin of all the other planets.
由于逆向自转太阳从西边升起
Because of this retrograde rotation, the Sun rises in the West
然后在东边落下
and sets in the East.
而且金星的一天很长
And the Venusian days are long ones.
一天的间隔如此长 从一次日出到下一次日出
The amount of time from one sunrise to the next
约等于8个地球月[解说有误 应为4个地球月]
is about 8 Earth months.
金星上漫长的一天
But the orbital pattern and long days
是非常难以忍受
are not what make Venus so intolerable.
部分原因是其恶劣的气候
In part, it's the wicked climate.
表面温度高达900华氏度[500摄氏度]
With a surface temperature of 900 ℉,
这里是太阳系中最恶劣的环境
Venus is the hottest planet in the Solar System.
旅行者经过这里将立即倒下
Travellers there would have their trip cut short in no time.
或许几秒钟
It would take a matter of seconds,
或许一秒钟然后走向地狱
maybe one second, before they were gone.
折磨致死
Roasted to death.
如果你是位宇航员没有穿宇航服降落到金星上
If you're an astronaut sitting on Venus without a space suit,
皮肤会立即烤干硬
then your skin's going to crisp up,
会像烤炉上的一只火鸡  不过还要快的多
you're gonna cook just like a turkey in an oven, except much faster even.
严酷的高温产生自温室效应
The unforgiving heat wave is created by a process called the "greenhouse effect",
温室效应维持着地球气候
the identical process that keeps Earth's climate in check
孕育了大量生命
and teeming with life.
在金星上却致使像这样的一片树林如何由
But a closer look at Venus tells us how this common trait
一片生机
can be a cycle of life.
变得一片死寂
And a cycle of death.
如今我们地球温度在提升
Today, our own temperature is on the rise,
科学家们发现也许就像发生于金星上那样
and scientists found the possible cause behind it up on Venus.
全球变暖的罪魁祸首温室气体
Global warming is a result of greenhouse gases
不断的增长 增长 增长
that are growing and growing.
导致我们生存更加更加困难
And therefore we're getting hotter and hotter.
当我们观察金星时 会说
And when we looked at Venus we said,
"啊哈 这里正发生着这一切"
"Aha! Here it is actually happening."
在90年代麦哲伦号探测器
In the 1990's, after the Magellan spacecraft
发射升空
was launched,
探测器飞向金星
planetary watchdogs began turning to Venus
看看温室效应最终能导致情况糟糕到何种程度
to surmise just how bad it could get here on Earth.
探测结果让我们了解很多地球及其大气将可能发生的一切
Space exploration has told us a lot about the Earth, and the environment in it.
事实上很多人谈到的温室效应所产生的气温变暖
And in fact the greenhouse effect, that everybody's talking here now with global warming,
正作用于现在的金星
was actually discovered on Venus.
对金星的更多了解
What they found out about Venus,
发现地球上的温室效应相对而言是多么弱小
shed new light on how fragile Earth's greenhouse effect really is.
金星并不总是这么热
Venus didn't always use to be this hot.
我们认为最初的金星表面类似于
We think that early in its history it was more
地球表面 甚至还有海洋
Earth-like on the surface and it lost its oceans
只是温室效应早已将其蒸发
due to what we call a "runaway greenhouse effect".
所以金星就是一个环境破坏的例子
So Venus is an example that certainly global change
发生于环境恶化的行星上
can happen on a planet in a sort of a worst case scenario.
我们没有变得像金星那样严重
You don't have to turn Earth into Venus before we're in trouble,
只是我们在这个方面不是最糟糕 但是正步步逼近
we just have to move a little bit in that direction, and we are moving in that direction.
研究金星的一个现实价值
But the real value of studying Venus,
就是建立我们的大气模型
it allows to test our climate models.
通过计算大气模型
Through computerized general circulation models, or GCM's,
科学家才能计算出地球上温度情况
scientists were able to calculate temperature increases on Earth,
计算利用了金星上温室气体量
based on the amount of greenhouse gases on Venus.
金星上的温室效应是如何生效的？
So, just how does Venus' greenhouse effect work
使这个行星如此炎热
and make the planet so hot?
这是生物圈2号
This is Biosphere 2,
位于亚利桑那州-圣凯瑟琳山上
located along the foothills of Arizona, Santa Catalina mountains,
一些研究员建立这个系统
it was built by a group of researchers to explore the idea
以助于将来的星际移民
of colonizing other planets.
这是世界上最大的温室
It is the largest greenhouse on Earth.
生物圈2号是个完美的温室
Biosphere is a perfect example of a greenhouse
因为这个巨型建筑完全由玻璃构成
because it's a big building with glass panes
让阳光完全透过这里非常温暖
that let the Sun in and it's really hot in here.
穿过玻璃的太阳光
The solar rays that penetrate the glass panes
使室内温度上升
cause the temperature inside to rise.
空气受热上升但是逃不出温室
The air heats up, but then the air cannot escape,
因为这些玻璃墙
cannot move vertically into the atmosphere because of the walls.
热量透过窗户温暖了这座建筑
The windows trap the heat, warm the building
给这些植物提供了合适的气候条件
and provide the plants and trees with a liveable climate.
金星上温室气体吸收大量太阳热量
On Venus, greenhouse gases don't exactly trap the Sun's heat,
同时又阻挡热量的逃离
but they greatly slow the rate at which it can escape.
任何行星上的温室气体的作用
The greenhouse effect on any planet is a situation where
都使得行星表面温度上升
the surface temperature becomes hotter
因为大气中的这些气体
because of gases in the atmosphere that trap the heat
在阳光穿越时吸收热量
while letting in the sunlight.
在金星上致命的温室气体
These same greenhouse gases that would prove to be fatal to us on Venus
却是地球生命不可缺少的
are essential to life on Earth.
没有温室效应
Without the greenhouse effect,
平均温度将低于零度
the average temperature would be far below freezing,
海洋将全部冰冻
the oceans would be totally, or almost totally frozen.
显然地球将不适宜生命
And it's not even clear if life would exist on the Earth.
我们总说金星温度如何高为什么温度这么高？
We talked about how hot it was but, why is it so hot?
原因在于大气成分
The answer has to do with the atmospheric composition.
几乎全是二氧化碳
It's almost all carbon dioxide there.
二氧化碳
Carbon dioxide or CO2,
构成金星大气的95%
makes up 95% of the Venusian atmosphere.
大量的二氧化碳吸收大量的热
And that high volume of gas traps more heat.
产生很强的温室效应
That's gonna give you a strong greenhouse effect
导致金星上如此热
and that's gonna make it really hot.
如此炎热的金星
And that's why it's so hot on Venus. It's an extreme example
是行星变暖的极端例子
of global warming.
在金星上火山是
On Venus, volcanoes
二氧化碳及其他一些气体的来源
are the natural spring source for CO2 and other gases.
形成了金星大气
It's a process atmospheric chemist Jeff Sutton
杰夫·萨顿正研究夏威夷的启劳亚火山
studies on Earth, at Hawaii's Kilauea volcano.
在这地面以下深处
Deep below the surface, atomic compounds ignite
物质在火山活动中燃烧生成二氧化碳
during volcanic activity to form CO2.
这些气体在高压高热的熔融岩石环境产生
The gas is born from the pressure created by the heat of molten rock,
也就是岩浆
or magma.
热岩浆上升到岩浆表面 产生岩浆顶蚀
It rises towards the surface and reaches the summit magma storage complex.
压力减小
The pressure is decreased on the magma,
过程中释放那些
and the effect of that is to allow gases
高压下困于岩浆内部的气体
that are trapped under the very high pressure
冒泡逃逸
to be released and bubble out.
金星表面有许多岩浆裂缝
The Venusian surface would likely have cracks in the lava
像这些一样
similar to these vents,
不断的排放气体
where gases escape into the air stream.
每天大约8000到30000吨的
Somewhere between 8,000 and 30,000 metric tons of
二氧化碳在岩浆中生成
carbon dioxide boil out of the magma chamber each day.
总计
And it amounts to something on the order of
约3.5到5百万吨每年
3.5 to 5 million tons per year.
而这仅仅只是地球上的一座火山
And that's just one volcano here on Earth.
金星上的活火山多的多
Venus has more active volcanoes
制造了多的多的温室气体
and that means more heat bouncing gases.
所有的这些二氧化碳
So, all the CO2
在金星大气中日积月累
just builds up in the atmosphere on Venus,
使温度不断升高
which just makes it hotter and hotter.
900华氏度[500摄氏度]的高温不是金星上唯一的气象
The 900℉ heat isn't the only trait that makes Earth's twin seem a menace.
离金星的高温地表约30英里[50千米]高的地方
30 miles above the scorching ground of Venus,
大气活动非常剧烈
there's havoc occurring on the planet
以致外层温度很低
that makes 900 ℉ feel like a cold front.
产生的闪电不断的分裂
Electrical mayhem, where split-second jolts
最多可以达到15000级
can reach 50,000?
每次闪电都产生高达1亿伏的电压
Each spark of light contains 100 million volts of electricity.
地球和金星上产生的闪电
Lightning occurs on both Earth and Venus
都是因为电荷不断聚集
when electrical charges
达到足够的程度最后释放而产生
store up enough energy until they release a spark.
米尔斯·奥本海姆 在波士顿大学教行星物理
Meers Oppenheim teaches Planetary Physics to students at Boston University.
像他这样的研究员 来波士顿科学馆进行实验
And researchers like him, get in on the action at Boston's Museum of Science.
进入这个闪电演示笼子里 这里有34个电极
In their cage-lighting exhibit, 30 foot-high domes
模拟金星上闪电的产生
motor up to simulate how lightning is generated on Venus.
然后 演示开始
And then it's show time.
看这个  我们生成了数百万伏的电压
Look at this, we're generating so many millions of volts on these domes
然后释放
that that voltage has to escape,
实际上它击穿了空气分子
and it's actually ripping molecules in the air apart.
笼顶的空气 跟金星上的云层一样
The air in the domes, like within the Venusian clouds,
云层气体分子摩擦聚集了大量电荷
stirs up the electrical distribution of tiny atomic molecules.
最终这些撕裂的分子产生了闪电 然后又循环
So the ripped molecules make that light as they reassemble themselves,
这就是闪电
and that's what a lightning bolt is.
宇宙粒子来自银河系外超新星爆发
Cosmic particles from exploding stars way out in the galaxy trigger lightning.
当它们袭击大气层时催生了闪电
When these hit the atmosphere, they provide that spark.
来自于宇宙深处的粒子
These are particles that come from way out in the Universe,
击中大气层 产生了带电粒子雨
hit the atmosphere and cause a shower of charged particles.
在金星上有超级闪电
On Venus, you probably have real lightning to an extreme extent,
带有巨大的能量 长达数英里
which contain an enormous amounts of energy and go for miles and miles.
每年闪电击中地球超过31亿次
On average, lightning hits the Earth more 3.1 billion times a year.
金星上击中地面的闪电次数却是
The number of times lightning hits the ground on Venus…
零
zero.
金星大气压比地球上大90倍
The atmospheric pressure on Venus is 90 times greater than on Earth,
是因为金星浓厚的大气的巨大重量
because the weight of the atmosphere created by gases is heavier.
阻止了闪电袭击金星地面
This prevents Venusian lightning from hitting hard ground,
而只能在云层间
instead, it is restrained to the clouds.
浓密大气的阻力如此大
There's just too much resistance in that very thick air
闪电无法穿越
for a lightning bolt to get through.
只能在云层间穿越
It's much easier for a lightning to discharge from to cloud to cloud.
金星云层看起来
And besides appearance,
像是地球上的普通云层
there's little else that's Earth-like about Venusian clouds.
实际上它的组成成分毒性剧烈
In fact, the main ingredient that creates them
会腐蚀人的皮肤
it's toxic enough to burn through human flesh.
清晨和黄昏我们可以在地球上看见金星像一颗星星
From Earth, you might be able to see Venus twinkle in the morning and evening skies like a star.
它毫不羞涩 明亮地挂在天空
Definitely not a wallflower. It's so bright in our sky
不仅仅因为离我们最近
not just because it's the closest planet to us,
更多的是因其高反照度
but because it's the most reflective planet.
缘于金星上覆盖着厚厚的
Because it turns out Venus is completely covered
反射阳光的云层
in this bright, reflective clouds.
80%的阳光都被金星云层反射了
80% of the Sun's light bounces off the clouds that blanket the planet.
尽管金星也有云 号称地球的姐妹星
But even in the clouds, Venus, our so called twin planet,
却显示出恶劣环境
manages to show an evil nature.
我们知道金星云层
We know that the clouds of Venus are made out of
由硫酸组成 像铅酸电池中的硫酸
sulphuric acid, basically like battery acid.
这些硫酸来源于二氧化硫
And that sulphuric acid is made by sulphur dioxide
产生于地表的火山
coming out of volcanoes on the surface.
就像另一种温室气体
Like its greenhouse cousin,
二氧化碳
carbon dioxide, or CO2,
气压推动下
gas pressure pushes sulphur dioxide
二氧化硫从火山中离开地表
to the surface through volcanic vents.
杰夫·萨顿 在夏威夷 启劳亚火山
It's the same gas chemist Jeff Sutton monitors carefully
仔细地监视这些二氧化硫
at Hawaii's Kilauea volcano.
这些气体特别是二氧化硫是有毒气体
The gases, the sulphur dioxide in particular, is the noxious, toxic gas
戴上防毒面具来保护肺
and we wear gas masks to protect our lungs
和呼吸道
and our airways,
因为二氧化硫会跟你的鼻子和咽喉
because sulphur dioxide combines with the moisture
里的水分结合生成硫酸
in your nose and throat and forms sulphuric acid.
硫酸很危险
Sulphuric acid is nasty stuff.
你不会让铅酸电池液接触自己
You don't want to splash battery acid on you,
你会很小心他们本质上是同一物质
you're careful not to do that. It's basically the same stuff.
所以最好不要把你的手伸进金星云层里
So it would not be good to suddenly stick your hand into the Venus clouds.
就算如此 旅行者如果能有幸穿过金星硫酸云
So, if a traveller to Venus could survive the acidic clouds,
幸免于闪电 有毒气体和高温
the lightning bolts, the toxic air and the heat,
他会看到一个怎样的金星表面？
just how would the Venusian surface look?
火山学家 杰夫·拜恩来自美国地质调查局(USGS) 走遍全球寻找那些
Vulcanologist Jeff Byrns, with the US Geological Survey, or USGS, circles the globe to understand
近日行星火山活动造成的结果
what drives volcanic activity on the inner planets.
当拜恩想象金星表面的情景时
When Byrns imagines the surface of Venus,
认为像这片黑色的火山岩地
he considers the dark, eerie wasteland of Kilauea's lava fields,
位于夏威夷 启劳亚火山上
on the big island of Hawaii.
这里非常有利于研究火山
It's very instructive to be able to come here and study this volcano
以对比金星表面发生的火山活动
to compare it to vulcanism that has occurred on the surface of Venus.
实际上我们来这里现场研究
We can actually come out here to the field and study things.
取得一些样本并仔细观察
We can actually take samples and look at them in detail.
地质学家预计金星上的火山
Geologists expect the amount of volcanoes on Venus
远远超过1500座的地球火山数量
far outnumbers the 1,500 or so on Earth.
一些学者估计
Some estimates range from 100,000 to
金星火山超过1百万座
over a million volcanic features on Venus.
由于如此多火山 岩浆地表
With that many volcanoes, lava rock
构成了70%的金星表面
makes up 70% of the Venusian surface.
就像启劳亚火山表面
Just like it makes up much of Kilauea's terrain.
岩浆冷却形成了坚硬的岩石地面
The ground becomes solid when the lava cools into hard rock.
地球上的这些岩石
Having rock on Earth is our best analogue
帮助我们理解其他行星上的类似地表
for trying to understand rocks on the other planets.
金星地面就像这些玄武岩
Basaltic rocks are the most similar to the Venusian plains.
玄武岩在金星上普遍存在
Basalt is the most common type of lava rock found on Venus
以及所有其他近日行星上
and throughout the inner Solar System.
矿石冷凝成小的玻璃或水晶形态
The minerals freeze into glass and small crystals.
变得完全不像岩浆
A total transformation from what lava looks like
流出火山时的样子
when it streams out of a volcano.
熔岩流经表面时
When lava is actively flowing across the surface,
炽热 火红的
it's incandescent and typically looks red.
很快地熔岩表面变得银光
Now, quickly it'll form a silvery sheen over the top of it
几周之后再变黑
and then, over a period of a few weeks, it'll turn black
就像我周围这些冷岩浆
such as lava we see around me here.
高达5英里[8千米] 玛特山是金星上最大的火山
At 5 miles high, Maat Mons is the largest volcano on Venus.
仍然活跃着 几条巨大的岩浆流往外冒
And it's left some tremendous lava channels in its wake,
像启劳亚火山一样
just like Kilauea did.
就像你看到的外面的这些结构
Now, as you can see the structure, we have levees here on the sides,
和里面这些结构一样
and then internal structures as well.
可能这些结构相似于
This is similar perhaps to how
金星表面被称作"宽度一定的长峡谷"的巨型通道
large channels, called "canali" formed on the surface of Venus.
不过比这些要大很多
However, they formed at a much larger scale.
大到数英里的"宽度一定的长峡谷"
Large enough to create seemingly endless miles of canali
形成独特的金星景色
across the Venusian landscape.
金星上又宽又深的"宽度一定的长峡谷"
Consistent in both width and depth,
比夏威夷上的要长的多
the canali are much longer on Venus than on Hawaii
因为金星上的环境条件
because of environmental conditions on the planet.
浓密的大气和炽热的高温
The dense atmosphere and hot temperature
岩浆的冷却速度很慢
slows the magma from cooling into solid rock.
少量的风而又没有雨
And with little wind and no rain to further cool the magma,
火山爆发后岩浆能在地表流上数月
lava can cut through the surface for months after an eruption
才慢慢硬化
before it hardens.
在金星上观察岩层
On Venus, if you did see layering, you would expect to see
将会是一层又一层的火山岩
layer after layer of volcanic rocks that would all be
黑色的 由玄武岩等物质构成
relatively black and basaltic in composition.
你可能会发现一些其他颜色
You would probably see little bits of colour
很可能是一些氧化铁
due to potentially oxidized iron, which would look red.
这些典型的玄武岩浆流
Typically, basaltic lava flows
呈玻璃状
are glassy enough
可以锋利到切掉你的手
that in fact you would cut your hand. They can be extremely sharp.
这些石块冷却后变成玻璃
They tend to quench and form glass.
金星天空布满浓云
And then there are the skies. That heavy, Venusian cloud cover
减弱了大部分的直射阳光
diffuses most of the direct sunlight.
金星白天比较昏暗
It would be a lot darker on the surface of Venus
相比之下地球就要亮的多
during the day that it would be here on Earth.
由于光线很散
Also, because the light is scattered very efficiently,
投下的影子很模糊
you tend to lose shadows.
所有一切都被照射着
So everything is lit fairly consistently across the surface
另外由于大气的特殊成分
and then, additionally, because of the composition of the atmosphere
所有一切都呈桔黄色
everything would tend to have more of an orangish tint to it.
山谷旁边 锯齿般的山脉
Besides canyons, jagged mountain ranges,
划破金星的天空
scrape the Venusian skies.
那是金星最高山脉--麦克斯韦山
The planet highest peak is on Maxwell Montes.
麦克斯韦山大约35000英尺[10600米]高
Maxwell is about 35,000 feet high.
这个高度
Which puts it at a
比地球任何山脉乃至珠穆朗玛峰还高许多
healthy distance above Mount Everest or any mountain on Earth.
珠穆朗玛峰大约29000英尺高
Everest is something about 29,000 feet high.
因此它大过地球上的所有东西
So it's definitely larger than anything on Earth.
金星已然超越
Our sister planet seems to have outdone
我们的七大自然奇观之一
one of our 7 natural wonders.
不过对比金星地面上另一种地质特征
But how would the Venusian terrain measure up
情况会怎么样呢？
against another geologic feature:
我们的大峡谷
our canyons.
科罗拉多大峡谷
The Grand Canyon.
在2亿5千万年来这条巨大的峡谷
A great chasm eroded over 250 million years
由科罗拉多河侵蚀而成
by the Colorado river.
几百万年前科罗拉多高原升起
When the Colorado plateau was uplifted millions of years ago,
使穿越峡谷的河流更加凶猛
it gave the water more energy to cut back through the canyon
冲击更多的岩石
and wear away the rocks.
金星上的大峡谷也可能是侵蚀而成的
The vast canyons on Venus may have also been formed by the erosion.
不过不是被河流侵蚀
But not by a river.
火山系统侵蚀出峡谷
Volcanic systems can erode canyons by having
液态岩浆流畅而不黏稠
fluid flow if it's very fluid, not very viscous.
岩浆像流水一样的侵蚀地面
Materials can erode similar to water.
科罗拉多大峡谷只是科罗拉多河流系统的一部分
And the Grand Canyon is only part of the Colorado river system,
不过即使把科罗拉多河流系统作为一个整体
but even looking at the Colorado river system as a whole,
都没有最长的金星峡谷长
it's not nearly as long as the longest channels on Venus.
如果古罗马人知道这些火山
Had the ancient Romans known about the volcanoes,
硫酸云
acidic clouds,
闪电
lightning bolts,
高毒空气
toxic air,
以及高温
and that scorching heat,
也许他们会给这颗恐怖的姐妹星
perhaps they may have named our evil twin planet
另取一个名字 而非爱与美之神
after something other than their goddess of beauty and love.
有些讽刺意味
There's irony there because, of course,
皆因罗马人不了解金星真实情况
the Greeks and Romans didn't know anything about the conditions on Venus.
而两千年后的现在
Then, here we are a couple of thousand years later
我们实际研究金星之后
and we're actually exploring this place,
发现那里一点也不符合我们的口味
and it's not quite so nice according to our tastes.
我们的姐妹星上的这些危险的状况
But how do the dangers found on our sister planet
跟水星上的宇宙碰撞相比又如何？
compare to the cosmic violence on Mercury?
离地球4800万英里[7700万千米]远
48 million miles away from Earth
水星 布满尘土的山和空旷的平原
Mercury's dust-covered hills and empty plains
不断延伸 看不到边
stretch as far as the naked eye can see.
表面的那种颜色
It's a colourless body.
不像我们在地球或火星上看到的
It does not have really any colours like you see on Mars or the Earth
甚至金星上也看不到
or even Venus, for that matter.
罗伯特·斯特罗姆 博士
Doctor Robert Strom,
来自亚利桑那大学 月球与行星实验室
with the University of Arizona's Lunar and Planetary Lab,
首席行星地质学专家 35年以上专业资历
has been a chief authority on planetary geology for more than 35 years.
水星最靠近太阳
Mercury is the innermost planet,
非常不同于太阳系里其他任何行星
and it's quite different than anything else in the Solar System.
水星是离太阳最近的行星 约3600万英里[5800万公里]
At 36 million miles, Mercury is the closest planet to the Sun.
没有卫星
The planet has no known moons.
没有大气
Mercury has no atmosphere.
黎明或黄昏时 在地球上肉眼可以看见水星
And it's a naked eye planet, visible on Earth during the twilight hours.
直径比地球小60%
With a diameter 60% smaller than Earth,
水星是太阳系里的小个子行星
Mercury is the Solar System's scrawniest planet.
太小而没有足够大引力
Much too strong to generate the strong gravitational field
无法维持大气
needed to retain an atmosphere.
万有引力取决于质量
Gravity depends upon the mass of the object.
质量越大引力越大
So the larger the mass, the more the gravity.
因此在水星上引力比较小
So, on Mercury, gravity is less on there.
由于水星上弱小的引力
Since the planet's gravity is so weak,
地球上重达150磅的物体
if you weighed 150 lbs on Earth,
在水星只有57磅
you'd only weigh 57 lbs on Mercury.
经过计算行星需要有足够大质量
Planet size matters when it comes
内部才会有足够地热而形成各种地质活动
to the internal heat needed to sustain geologic activity.
行星内部没有了地质对流
The internal convection currents that drive geology stop
总而言之 里面冻结了
and, in general, it just freezes up.
因此无法形成地质活动
And there's no way to sustain that geological activity.
很久以前水星上就是如此了
And that happened to Mercury a long time ago.
可能就在水星诞生几亿年之后
Probably after less than a billion years of its life.
水星上曾经也大量陨星袭击
The days when the planet beat with the strong pulse
造成火山活动和不断的地震
that produced volcanic and tectonic Mercury-quakes,
不过这是很久之前的事了
are long gone.
水星是一颗死星吗？
Is Mercury a dead planet?
这取决于你对"死"的理解
It depends on what you mean by "dead".
水星内部还活跃吗？恐怕不是
Is it internally active now? Probably not.
也许是完全的死寂
It's probably not active at all.
基本上就是一颗死星
It is essentially a dead planet
已经这样40多亿年了
and has been dead for about 4 billion years.
水星虽然没有任何活力仍然以某些方式运动着
For a nearly lifeless planet, Mercury still has some movement.
古罗马人尊称水星为墨丘利--为众神使者
Named by the ancient Romans after the swift-footed messenger god,
水星绕太阳公转仅需88地球日
Mercury orbits the Sun in 88 Earth days.
比任何其他太阳系行星都要快
The fastest of any planet.
水星自己本身的自转
But when it comes to the time it takes Mercury to spin on its own axis,
是所有行星中最慢的[解说有误 水星自转不是最慢]
the planet holds the record for being the slowest.
持续近180天[解说有误 180天是太阳日 非自转周期]
Length of time: Around 180 Earth days,
大约半年[同错]
about half a year.
由于太阳的巨大引力产生"潮汐摩擦"作用
The Sun's gravitational force creates a tidal friction within Mercury
减慢了水星的自转周期
which slows down its speed as it spins on its axis.
导致水星的一年比一天要短[有误 应是一天比一年短]
This means a year on Mercury is shorter than a day on the planet.
缓慢的自转形成水星上的特殊气候
And that sluggish rotation gives Mercury a somewhat peculiar weather forecast.
长达6个月 面向阳光的一面表面温度高达800华氏度[425摄氏度]
For 6 months, the side exposed to the Sun reaches 800 ℉.
背面温度则低于零下300华氏度[-185摄氏度]
On the other side, the temperature drops to -300 ℉.
面向太阳的一面长时间的高温
It has a long time to heat up on the side facing the Sun
背面则长时间的低温
and a long time to cool down on the other side.
所以水星上才有这样巨大的温差
That's why it has a huge temperature extremes.
因为水星接近太阳
Despite its close proximity to the Sun,
水星是行星家族中的污点
Mercury is a bit of a black ship in the planetary family.
天空永远是单调的星空
Its skies always seem like starry nights.
黑暗的
The skies would be black.
我们地球的天空之所以是蓝色的
The reason we have blue skies on the Earth
是因为地球大气
is because of our atmosphere.
空气分子散射了阳光中的蓝光
Nitrogen scatters light preferentially in the blue,
于是地球的天空呈蓝色
and so that's why the sky looks blue.
水星没有大气因此天空黑暗
Mercury doesn't have an atmosphere so the sky would be black.
根据罗马神话--墨丘利
Legend holds that Mercury, the Roman god,
发明了拳击运动
invented the sport of boxing.
水星也如此的进行了一场长期拳击
And this is one planet that's taken the lion's share in the ring.
水星呈被数百万的陨石 小行星
Mercury has had millions of meteors and asteroids explode on its surface,
袭击其没有大气保护的表面
because it doesn't have an atmosphere to protect it.
地球大气层很好的抵御了大多数袭击
Our atmosphere guards Earth from most impacts,
像一个力场
like a force field.
当小个的物体袭来
When a small object slams into it,
速度通常比子弹还要快10被
usually at more than 10 times the speed of a bullet,
与空气分子产生激烈摩擦高温蒸发逸尽
the collision with air molecules vaporizes it into a gas.
地球不被陨星袭击
The Earth is shielded from small impacting objects
全靠这神奇的大气层
by this wonderful thing that we call the atmosphere.
这些小物体
And for small objects, weak objects,
完全被摧毁
they will be completely destroyed
在离地面很高的大气中
by those forces long before they get to the geologic surface of our planet.
水星上没有大气
On Mercury, without that atmosphere,
陨星直接全速撞击水星表面
the asteroids and meteors smack down at full throttle.
导致水星上拥有太阳系里最多的坑
This makes Mercury the most heavily cratered planet in the Solar System.
遍布水星 你找不到一块没有坑的地方
You cannot take a step on Mercury without encountering an impact crater.
1974年水手10号探测器
Back in 1974, the Mariner 10 space probe
绘制出了水星一半的表面
mapped half the planet's surface
包括一个太阳系中最大的坑
including the largest crater ever surveyed in the Solar System.
这个特征最显著的陨石坑被称作卡洛里斯盆地
The most prominent feature, is a feature called the "Caloris Basin",
这个坑如此大
which is a very large impact crater
直径可能有900英里[1500千米]
that is about maybe 900 miles in diameter.
直径900英里[1500千米]
900 miles in diameter.
比整个德克萨斯州还要大200英里[300千米]
That's a couple of hundred miles broader than the entire state of Texas.
研究人员推测
Researchers speculate the iron meteorite
可能是铁质小行星的剧烈撞击
that made that impact,
在撞击地表前伸展到超过60英里[95千米]大
stretched for more than 60 miles before it crashed into the surface.
撞击后瞬间
Moments after impact,
产生的地震波汇聚于相反的一点
seismic waves converged at the antipodal point,
刚好在水星背面的对应点上
the spot on the exact opposite side of the planet.
冲击所形成的地震波
The seismic waves, the shock waves from this thing travelled
几乎同时 汇集到水星的另一面
and they concentrated simultaneously around the other side of the planet
撕裂着地表
and literally shook apart the surface.
在地震波的搅动下 扭曲杂乱地混在一起
The seismic turbulence jumbled up the crust and twisted the terrain
形成不规则岩石地表
into unusual rock formations.
这些奇异的地表
There is all this weird terrain,
有个术语叫"怪异地形"
in fact the technical term is "weird terrain".
看着那些奇异杂乱的丘陵
Cause you look at it and it's just weird, it's jumbled up and hilly
按地质活动成因是说不通的
and it doesn't make any sense according to most geological activities.
看上去地表好像被"人"粗暴地
It's just very rough and looks as though somebody kind of
舀上来而停止下降
scooped up the surface and just dropped it down.
陨石坑瞬间变成天然的山
Pre-existing craters suddenly became crude hills
大约6英里宽 1英里高
some 6 miles wide and a 1 mile high.
地表在几秒钟内
In fact, the amount of surface elevation could have been
就升起高达1至2千米
on the order of 1 Km or 2 in just a few seconds.
非常惊人
It would have been horrendous.
科学家无法确切的弄清楚
Scientists have no way of knowing exactly when
卡洛里斯盆地何时形成的
the "Caloris" impact happened.
不过他们可以想象某个事件
But they can surmise one thing,
如果这样的巨大的小行星袭击地球
if an asteroid the same size crashed into the Earth,
撞击造成巨大灾难
the impact would be catastrophic.
将毁灭人类文明
And wipe out human civilization.
无数陨星在水星上留下疤痕
Countless meteor and asteroid impacts have left Mercury
形成各样的环形山和陨石坑
scarred with dents and crater rings.
如今水星像个筋疲力竭的僵尸
Today the planet looks beaten, a terrestrial corpse.
像水星一样地球表面也很易受撞击
Like Mercury, Earth's surface is vulnerable to bombardment.
亚利桑那陨石坑
And Arizona's Meteor Crater
是地球上保持最完整 最相似于水星陨石坑
is one of our most preserved and mercurian craters.
这片荒芜的盆地有利于地质学家了解
The desert basin has given geologists a better understanding
陨星撞击水星表面所发生的
of what happens when a meteor strikes Mercury's surface.
地震波的能量的冲击力
Upon impact, energy from the shock wave
炸裂了地表 击飞数吨的石块
rips through the surface and moves tons of rock upward
形成了陨石坑
to shape the crater.
飞溅的石头离开这碗状坑底
And that flow of rock excavated this bowl-shaped cavity
散落在周围数英里形成这奇特景观
and deposited debris on the landscape for kilometres around.
撞击的能量同时也形成了这坑壁
The same energy swept up the crater walls
造成了我周围升起的这些岩层
and caused the flat plane layers of rock behind me to actually be uplifted.
在巨大撞击的作用下
And the rock, under the influence of shock
使得那些易碎的石头
wasn't behaving "brittley" like rock does,
变得具有韧性
but more like taffy.
陨石坑都有这样的特点
This is one of the hallmarks of impact craters.
不仅仅在这个陨石坑里
No only here at Meteor Crater
太阳系所有的陨石坑都如此
but anywhere in the Solar System.
想象一下造成水星上卡洛里斯盆的巨大小行星
But imagine if the mighty object that formed Mercury's Caloris Basin
撞击在这个亚利桑那陨石坑的地方
crashed down on the site of Meteor Crater.
将产生巨大的爆炸
It would be a massive explosion,
高温而融化的陨石碎片
with chunks of molten material
从地面飞起
flying around the Earth ballistically,
冲进大气层
re-entering the Earth's atmosphere
造成巨大的陨石碎片雨
and causing massive meteor showers everywhere.
冲击波将袭击7500英里[12000千米]范围的地面
For nearly 7,500 miles, the shockwave would rip up the soil
产生高达2000英尺[60米]的海啸
and stir up tsunamis with 200-foot waves.
地球上产生的最大海啸
Massive tsunamis would propagate around the Earth
淹没几乎所有的海岸
and inundate much of the world's coastlines.
从地球上抹去内华达州--拉斯维加斯
It would flatten Las Vegas, Nevada,
犹他州--盐湖城
the cities of Salt Lake City, Utah,
加利福尼亚--旧金山
San Francisco, California,
以及洛杉矶摧毁于瞬间
and Los Angeles would vanish in a split second.
冲击波的作用
Shockwaves from the impact
沿着地球表面波及
would propagate through the solid Earth
数千英里之外的地方
thousands of miles from the site of an impact like that.
这些地震波将汇聚于
Those seismic waves would converge
撞击处相对立的地方
at the impact's antipodal point,
位于马达加斯加的海岸
off the coastline of Africa's Madagascar.
印度洋底部
At the bottom of the Indian Ocean.
瞬间巨大的山脉将从海底升起
Suddenly, a mountain range would explode through the ocean floor,
形成一个像水星上那样的"怪异地形"
and crash up to form that weird Mercurian terrain.
如此难以置信的大地震
Like an unbelievable earthquake,
将作用于整个地球
probably everywhere on Earth for an object that large.
地表的陨石坑大小将
Meteor Crater would be a nick in the surface
相等于水星上的
compared to the Mercurian gash left behind
卡洛里斯盆地
from a Caloris-type impact.
吞噬掉大约四分之一的美国大陆
The gouge would consume a quarter of the continental United States.
如此大的小行星
An object of that size
将干掉大部分的美国西海岸
would eliminate a large portion of the West coast of the US
如果某天它落到亚利桑那
if it fell, say, on Arizona.
实际上西海岸瞬间就被改变
It would literally change the coastline in an instant.
回到水星
Back on Mercury,
这些陨石坑是太阳系的一个标志
those craters give it an iconic stature in the Solar System.
其中一些非常神秘
And some of this pockmarks harbour mysteries.
当位于波多黎各的阿雷西博天文台的雷达
When the radar at Puerto Rico's Harecibo Observatory
聚焦于水星极地
honed in on Mercury's poles,
收集到的信息迷惑了研究人员
it picked up something that left researchers befuddled.
冰 太阳系最热的行星之一
Ice, of all things. One of the hottest bodies in the Solar System
极地居然有冰 那里有冰的原因是
and it has ice in the Poles. And the reason it has ice there, is because
水星表面有大量陨石坑
Mercury is a heavily cratered surface,
两极地区的陨石坑内
and so craters in the polar regions,
完全处于阴影下
the inside of them, are constantly in shadow.
这是由于水星极轴垂直于公转平面
That's because Mercury is vertical relatively to the plane of its orbit.
一些坑内永远也见不到阳光
So some crater floors never receive light or heat from the Sun.
但是水星上没有任何水源
But with no obvious water source on the planet
问题在于
that begs the question:
冰怎么到达那里？
How did the ice get there?
科学家猜测可能是来自于彗星
Scientists believe the mystery ice could have come from a comet.
由石块 尘土 气体和冰组成的彗星
Comprised of rock, dust, gases and ice,
来自于太阳系外部
comets come from the outer reaches of the Solar System,
那里温度比较低
where the temperatures are much colder.
那些冰仅仅只是呆在坑底部的
Could this ice just be on the bottom
永久的阴影里
of permanently shaded craters?
还是被尘土覆盖而隔离了阳光
Or could it be ice that sort of covered up by a layer of dust,
我们并不真正清楚
which is shielding it from sunlight? We really don't know.
除了彗星撞击之外
Besides these comet collisions,
水星上还有一些坑
there is yet another type of crater on the planet.
不是由外部撞击所形成的
And they weren't formed by anything that fell from the sky.
相反 类似于产生这些洞穴的地球自然力
Instead, an Earth-like force of nature created these holes
由水星内核深处的能量产生
and it generated deep from within the planet's core.
水星
Mercury
科学家对其地表更近的观察后
A closer look at its terrain by scientists
发现一些坑有些不同
reveals that some of its craters could have been formed from something
不同于小行星 彗星和陨星的撞击坑
other than asteroids, comets and meteors.
我们知道 水星的地质演化中
We do understand that the dominant geologic process that affected Mercury,
陨石撞击坑是主要的影响
or at least Mercury's surface is impact cratering.
第二大地质演化作用
The second most important geologic process
就是水星火山
to affect Mercury is vulcanism.
虽然还没有有力证据
Although we haven't seen any definite evidence
证明水星火山的存在
of volcanoes on Mercury,
我们认为水星过去有过火山爆发
we do expect that there have been volcanic eruptions in the past.
这个遥远的奶牛牧场 离凤凰山以北约3小时车程
This remote cow pasture, a 3 hours drive North of Phoenix,
这里也许能揭示水星上火山活动历史
might contain a telling link to Mercury's volcanic history.
坑状的山是死火山的圆锥形口
The cratered hills are extinct cinder-cone volcanoes,
地质学家猜测跟水星上的火山相似
and geologists suspect similar ones can be found on Mercury.
这些是圆锥型的死火山
This is a cinder cone.
你可以看到我身后的巨大火山口中央
You can see behind me, there's a large crater in the centre,
非常典型的火山口
which is typical of cinder cones.
这些火山口跟水星上会有所不同
These volcanoes do have their differences with Mercury's cinder cones.
因为水星重力较小
Because Mercury has less gravity, we would expect that the
我们猜想会比较宽大和平整
cinder cones that formed to be much wider and much flatter.
所有火山都是由于岩浆的压力的爆发
All volcanoes erupt when the pressure from the magma, or molten rock inside,
远远超过了岩石可以承受的力量
is greater than the strength of the rock containing it.
有两个原因使压力增加
Pressure increases for two reasons:
过多的岩浆或过多的气体
too much magma and too much gas.
当火山里的压力增加时
And when pressure increases in a volcano,
通常有出口使得压力得以释放
it usually has one place to go.
岩浆漫及表面喷涌而出
Lava comes up to the surface and erupts explosively.
这里有一条管且道又有一个喷火源
You have a vent area and you have what's called the fire fountain.
如果压力突然剧增
If the pressure is great enough,
这力量能使岩浆喷射100英尺[30米]高
its force can spew lava higher than 100 feet on Earth.
但是由于水星的弱小引力
But on Mercury, with such low gravity,
岩浆也许能喷到30层楼高
the fountain could eject lava 30 storeys high.
通过亚利桑那的这些死火山
While these cinder cones in Arizona
我们人类相比水星火山
may illustrate our shared volcanic heritage with Mercury,
虽然亲自见证过火山爆发
to witness an eruption there first hand,
与死火山的形成
and watch the cinder cones form,
但却是一种完全不同的体验
would be a whole other experience.
首先由于没有大气 羽状烟尘和碎片
First, without an atmosphere, a plume of ashen smoke and debris,
不会飘散很广
wouldn't billow across the landscape.
这些物质直接进入深空
That material would go into, essentially,
因为没有大气
a vacuum of space because Mercury doesn't have an atmosphere.
这些物质会散碎的多
So that material would break out much more.
在水星上听不到火山爆发的轰鸣
Also on Mercury, you wouldn't be able to hear the loud eruption.
也是因为水星没有大气
Since Mercury has no atmosphere,
没有可以传播声音的介质
there is no way of transmitting sound, so if you were on Mercury
所以如果你在水星上弹吉他 四弦琴或钢琴
and playing a guitar or a ukulele or a piano,
你什么也听不到
you would not hear anything,
这里没有大气传播声音
because there is no atmosphere to transmit that sound.
所以是完全寂静的
So it would be just complete silence.
1974年水手10号探测器仅仅只绘制了
Back in 1974, Mariner 10 surveyed only 45%
45%的水星表面
of Mercury's surface on a fly-by mission.
30年后NASA(美国航空航天局)发射了另一颗信使号空间探测器
30 years later, NASA launched the Messenger spacecraft.
它将绘制整个水星表面
The satellite will map the entire planet
发回给这些已经急不可待的
and transmit data to eager scientists
有大量问题需要解决的科学家
with a deluge of unanswered questions.
急切地想看看水星的另一面不知道那里是怎样的
I want to see the other side. I don't know what's over there
这个已经烦扰我35年了
and that's been bugging me for 35 years.
是否会跟我们看见的一面一致？还是有许多不同寻常之处？
Is it like the side we saw, or is it something very unusual and different?
尽管拿到这次探索的资料
But even with resources being earmarked for future exploration
太阳系这个又皱又小的水星最后
of this rumpled dwarf in the Solar System,
实际无论多不同或多么相同
exactly how different or similar we really are
我们依然会有更多的问题待解决
may be left up in the air.
尽管水星和金星环境恶劣
Despite the harsh conditions on Mercury and on Venus,
进一步的观察显示其不如古代想象般美好
a close look around our own backyards reveals the good,
只是又糟又丑的近日行星
the bad and the ugly of the inner planets.
宇宙如此广袤
The Universe is this vast, vast thing.
而我们  位于这个小点上
And here we are, sitting on this little pinprick.
但是我们并不孤独
But we are not isolated.
我们观察其他行星上发生的一切
We see things that happen on these other planets,
过去的恐怖可怕的变化
with tremendous climatic changes
发生于某个时期
in the past that have happened in a very short period of time,
也可能发生于地球上
and that could happen on the Earth.
最后 我们越来越丰富的知识
Ultimately, it enriches our knowledge of who we are,
认识这独立无二的珍贵环境
and how unique and how rare an environment like ours
了解我们人类处于这样的宇宙中
and even creatures like us, might be in the Universe.
在宇宙的这个角落进化 探索
And that evolution, that exploration, that turning the corner,
我们追寻新思想新发现
that discovery of new ideas is what we're all about.
永远有着光明的未来
There is a bright future.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing